<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sparql xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/sparql-results#'>
	<head>
		<variable name='o'/>
	</head>
	<results>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>Many religious refugees settled in and around the town of Krefeld, which formed part of the territory ruled by the House of Orange, under which the town received the status of a “religious asylum”. The persecutions began in the Bishopric of Würzburg. Concurrent with the events in Würzburg, Prince-Bishop Johann von Dornheim would embark upon a similar series of large-scale witch trials in the nearby territory of Bamberg. The witch hunts expanded into Baden following its reconquest by Tilly while the Imperial victory in the Palatinate opened the way for their eventual spread to the Rhineland. The Rhenish electorates of Mainz and Trier both witnessed mass burnings of suspected witches in this period. During this time the witch hunts also continued their unchecked growth, as new and increased incidents of alleged witchcraft began surfacing in the territories of Westphalia. The persecutions continued until the death of Ehrenberg in July, 1631. The excesses of this period inspired the Jesuit scholar and poet Friedrich Spee (himself a former "witch confessor") to author his scathing legal and moral condemnation of the witch trials, the Cautio Criminalis. This influential work was later credited with bringing an end to the practice of witch-burning in some areas of Germany and its gradual abolition throughout Europe.</literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>The Thirty Years' War was a war fought primarily in Central Europe between 1618 and 1648. One of the most destructive conflicts in human history, it resulted in eight million fatalities not only from military engagements but also from violence, famine, and plague. The deadly clashes ravaged Europe; 20 percent of the total population of Germany died during the conflict. One of its enduring results was 19th-century Pan-Germanism, when it served as an example of the dangers of a divided Germany and became a key justification for the 1871 creation of the German Empire.</literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>The House of Orange gave the town of Krefeld and the surrounding region the status of a religious asylum. </literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>The growth of Krefeld began in that century, partially because Krefeld was one of few towns spared the horrors of the Thirty Years' War (1618–1648). During the 17th century Mennonite settlers transformed the “insignificant little town” of Krefeld into a bustling capital of the linen trade. 

Protestant minorities, such as the Mennonites, were excluded from political office and landownership. Through family connections, they created a network or transfer system for commodities, money, and information which endowed them with considerable economic advantages that were collaboratively exploited (as in an association). The Rhenish political environment and system provided tolerance and protection, was socially open and allowed the economic success of minorities. </literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>The population increased due to the influx of young men attracted to Krefeld by the higher earnings and ample employment opportunities resulting from industrial growth. Textile operatives were recruited from amongst the local population. Locals succeeded in staving off the influx of outsiders into this realm, which they considered their exclusive preserve. Newcomers were pressed into the “residentiary” and tertiary sectors. This prosperity influenced the expansion of tertiary sectors in Krefeld.</literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>The Krefeld textile industry and trading companies provided all the services and materials required to manufacture ecclesiastical fabrics: colour-fast yarns, equipment, design drawings workshops, point paper designs and punched cards to weave patterns. The influx of Catholic workers from the surrounding region meant that many new churches were constructed in the new districts on the outskirts of the town towards the end of the 19th century and beginning of the 20th century and consequently the demand for ecclesiastical textiles was high. Orders were completed quickly despite the complicate handicraft involved. Depending on the pattern, a weaver could weave the fabric for a priest’s vestment in two to five days on average. Velvet brocade took more than 10 days. The fabric was then cut out, sewn together and embroidered so that the order was completed within 2 to 3 weeks. The Krefeld producers of ecclesiastical textiles had a good reputation for their very high quality products and for the colour fastness of the fabrics.

Liturgical vestments and fabrics were still produced as was usual in the manufactories of the 19th century. The manufacture of ecclesiastical fabrics gave at least some of them the opportunity of employment.  In this sector weaving was still carried on manual looms because only short lengths of cloth were required as each item was individually designed.  It was not economical to use the mechanised looms to produce the small quantities of very high quality fabrics interwoven with gold and silver threads.</literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>Krefeld’s industrial dynamism stood in marked contrast to the helplessness of many languishing linen centres unable to cope with the prospective loss of their main outlet, the English market. In the course of the 18th century, this export market virtually dried up, supplanted by the meteoric rise of a resilient Northern Irish linen trade. Bolstered by governmental subsidies and a protective tariff, the Ulster linen industry not only established its ascendency within Great Britain but soon became a formidable competitor in the world at-large.

The Krefeld textile industry moved toward the manufacture of silk products, as its principal source of employment. The former linen industry provided a solid basis from which to launch this change. Silk barons found no serious difficulties in gathering an able workforce. The linen weavers, in and around Krefeld, eagerly turned to silk weaving: the new trade offered them prospects of considerably higher earnings and more regular employment opportunities. Social and financial cohesiveness among the elite effectively barred all outsiders from entry into Krefeld’s silk and velvet trades. These close-knit ties had been evolved by this energetic and ambitious minority in response to persecution.

The old linen industry provided a solid basis from which to launch this change (“Displacing thus the linen trades,” writes Gerhard von Beckerath, “they [i.e., the von der Leyens] struck roots with their silk industry on ground prepared by the Julich linen merchant-manufacturers). The strategic importance of an existing industrial framework in creating “external economics” (external economies of scale) for the newly developing trade is well established. Here it became most apparent in the sphere of early labour recruitment. Krefeld confirmed, unmistakably, Adam Smith’s contention on how minor the differences between working on linen and silken products were. </literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>Workers were adept at learning the new tasks and skills required for silk production from foreign experts: tasks and dexterity required uniquely for the silk industry. The workers, transferring from linen to silk, carried over a tradition of industrial discipline and habits of work ingrained in them by generations of service in a well-developed and exacting domestic industry. The fact that the social environment was favourable to the course of economic development is particularly striking in this instance, for the rise of the Krefeld silk industry coincides, both with the decline of the same trade in guild-dominated Cologne and with Frederick the Great’s lack of success in establishing silk manufacture in Berlin. During the 17th century Mennonite settlers transformed the “insignificant little town” of Krefeld into a bustling capital of the linen trade. 
Through family connections, Mennonites created a network or transfer system for commodities, money, and information which endowed them with considerable economic advantages that were collaboratively exploited (as in an association). The political environment and Rhenish system provided tolerance and protection and was socially open. It allowed minorities to become economically successful.</literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>Many workshops producing ecclesiastical fabrics in Krefeld had to close down. Despite the severe losses suffered by the ecclesiastical fabric business as a result of the Second Vatican Council the Gotzes company was able to hold out for a long time at its original location. Over time, the number of skilled manual weavers declined. In 1989, the last weaver dies. the Gotzes company, closes the weaving workshop and just maintains sales. </literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>Despite the end of the Gotzes enterprise, it was important to the entrepreneur that the last Krefeld silk weaving workshop with its Jacquard looms in their authentic place should be preserved for posterity. He contacted the town of Krefeld and initiated a process which finally led to the Association of Friends acquiring the property and its contents from the Maus family with the aid of funds made by available by the Kulturstiftung NRW and the Sparkassenstiftung Krefeld (cultural trusts) in 2000. Since that year, the Association of Friends has run the former weaving workshop for ecclesiastical textiles as a museum supported by a team consisting mainly of volunteers. The active volunteers and the members of the Association of Friends now strive to literally keep the history of the premises alive. Weavers and point paper designers amongst others contribute to this by demonstrating what it was once like to work in the weaving workshop at Hubert Gotzes. The former cutting and embroidery rooms are now the setting for temporary exhibitions and demonstrations of former craftsmanship which are in most cases connected with the history of the building or the “Town like Silk and Velvet”. Apart from gaining impressions of past history, there is always something new to see and experience at the Haus der Seidenkultur. Mr. Stangenberg (Member of the Town Council) and Paul Günther Schulte (Town Archivist) and Dr. Stratmann (Deputy Director of the Museums in Burg Linn) campaigned to preserve the industrial monument and became founding members of the Association of Friends. </literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>Düsseldorf government building officer Franz Anton Umpfenbach drew up the designs for the 7th expansion of Krefeld.  A strict geometric road network was planned. The existing road diagonally traversing Alte Linner Strasse, was retained as the historical route to Linn. Luisenplatz and Albrechtplatz were developed as new public squares. Street naming: the streets running north to south were given the names of members of the Prussian royal family.  “Crown Prince Street” was a reference to the then Crown Prince Friedrich Wilhelm IV who visited Krefeld in 1833. The other street names also refer to members of Prussian nobility, Luisenstrasse (Louise of Prussia), Mariannenstrasse (Marianne of Oranien-Nassau), Elisabethstrasse (Elisabeth of Bavaria).</literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>Prussian government in Berlin approves the plans for the 7th expansion of Krefeld. These plans set out the expansion in an easterly direction covering what is now known as the “Crown Prince District”.</literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
		<result>
			<binding name='o'>
				<literal>The prosperity of the silk and velvet ecclesiastical textile industry in Krefeld. In the 18th century, sophisticated capitalist arrangements and sustained proto-industrial growth became the order of the day. This development is as true of Krefeld as it is of the towns in the Wupper valley. By the close of the 18th century the story to be told is one of rapid urbanization and sizable accumulation of wealth in the wake of impressive successes registered by the Rhenish textile wares on markets throughout the world. Focus is on the achievements of these enclaves of prospering proto-industrialization and the historical significance of an expanding domestic manufacture. 
Krefeld profited from Cologne’s decline. Krefeld was sufficiently close to Cologne to claim the role as regional silk centre, which the medieval metropolis was being forced to abdicate. Krefeld‘s proximity to the Netherlands enabled the area to take advantage of what the Dutch silk industry, then amongst the most advanced in the world, could access in terms of new techniques and methods of production. Krefeld, led by the von der Leyens imported from Holland the initial tools, the equipment and, most important, those skilled craftsmen who were to instruct the local population in the various tasks of making silk products.
Comparative historical investigations emphasize the peculiarities of German development, such as its “revolution from above" or the “Prussian way" of agrarian modernization, in order to explain why that development deviated so clearly from the path taken by the 1st industrial nation Britain (whose development is more or less implicitly taken as the normal path of modernization). Such studies have attributed great importance to the weakness of the German bourgeoisie which is judged responsible for a lack of entrepreneurial talent, and of markets for which only conscious state action could adequately compensate. Mercantilism, bureaucracy, and enlightened absolutism are thus seen as substitutes for the spontaneous capitalism and a broad middle stratum of society that allegedly propelled British development. 
The true carriers of industrial development in these textile regions were individual capitalist entrepreneurs. These started at the end of the medieval period as well-to-do peasants engaged in trade as a side-line, evolving later into specialized traders and “putter-owners” and finally as merchants and factory owners with hundreds of dependent workers. The successful Krefeld silk industry was built almost exclusively by private entrepreneurship. In contrast, the less successful Berlin industry was heavily dependent upon the assistance of the Prussian state. Production of more specialized patterned and fashionable silk fabric and ribbon remained under the merchants’ direct control in Krefeld itself. </literal>
			</binding>
		</result>
	</results>
</sparql>
